Guide to the Clara T. Evans bookplate collection, circa 1740-1960
Evans, Clara T. bookplate collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Clara T. Evans bookplate collection, circa 1740-1960 (bulk 1890-1940).
8027
Clara Therese, Evans
33 volumes (circa 3.5 linear feet);
Correspondence, Newspapers, Printed Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Bookplates from a variety of countries and time periods, mainly American and European. Armorial and pictorial plates are included, as well as those consisting of portraits, family crests, or mottoes.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Clara Therese Evans (also known as Mrs. Hubert Evans) was evidently a staff member at Ware Memorial Library, Columbia University, who collected bookplates. She corresponded with numerous libraries, other collectors, and some artists in search of bookplates to add to her collection.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Bookplates from a variety of countries and time periods, mainly American and European. Armorial and pictorial plates are included, as well as those consisting of portraits, family crests, or mottoes. Plates include engravings, etchings, lithographs, wood engravings, woodcuts, watercolors, and photographs; styles include classical, imitation Celtic, imitation Gothic, symbolist, cubist, art nouveau, and others. Bookplate designers featured include Elisha Brown Bird, F.C. Blank, Oscar T. Blackburn, Daniel B. Fearing, Edwin Davis French, Otto W. Fuhrmann, W.F. Hopson, Dan Burne Jones, William Jordan, J.W. Jameson, Arthur N. McDonald, Sidney L. Smith, Ismael Smith, Leslie Victor Smith, J. Winfred Spenceley, Wilbur Macey Stone, Margaret Ely Webb. The collection is only partially organized, so every volume contains some bookplates that are extraneous to its main focus. A few newspaper clippings, and letters to Mrs. Evans from various libraries, other collectors, and artists, are interspersed with the bookplates.
Book owners whose bookplates are in the collection include Charles Dickens, David Garrick, James Branch Cabell, Thomas Bird Mosher, book collector George A. Plimpton, Winfred Porter Truesdell, William Whewell, and numerous institutions including Avery Library, Columbia College (New York City), the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Ohio State University, Bangor (Me.) Public Library, Harvard College Library, other library collections at Harvard University, Princeton University Library, and the Grolier Club.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Evans, Clara Therese,; Bird, Elisha Brown.; Blackburn, Oscar T.; Blank, F. C.; Cabell, James Branch.; Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870.; Evans, John William, b. 1855.; Fearing, Daniel B.(Daniel Butler), 1859-1918.; French, Edwin Davis, 1851-1906.; Fuhrmann, Otto W.(Otto Walter); Garrick, David, 1717-1779.; Hopson, William Fowler, 1849-1935.; Jameson, J. W.; Jones, Dan Burne.; Jordan, William,; McDonald, Arthur N.; Mosher, Thomas Bird, 1852-1923.; Plimpton, George A.(George Arthur), 1855-1936.; Pyle, Howard, 1853-1911.; Smith, Ismael, 1886-1972.; Smith, Leslie Victor.; Smith, Sidney Lawton, 1845-1929.; Spenceley, J. Winfred(Joseph Winfred), 1865-1908.; Stone, Wilbur Macey.; Truesdell, Winfred Porter.; Webb, Margaret Ely.; Whewell, William, 1794-1866.; Avery Library.; Bangor Public Library.; Columbia College (New York, N.Y.); Grolier Club.; Harvard College Library.; Harvard University.; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.); Ohio State University.Library.; Princeton University.Library.
Subjects:
Bookplates.; Heraldic bookplates.; Scenic bookplates.; Book collectors.
Form and Genre Terms:
Bookplates.; Armorial bookplates.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Miscellaneous unmounted or unsorted plates (Volume Bd. Ms. 1)
- Lesser nobility, Jacobean, 1700-1745; Chippendale, 1753-1773, circa 1600-1800 (Volume Bd. Ms. 2)
- Lesser nobility; also U.S. presidents (facsimiles), Charles Dickens, and David Garrick (Volume Bd. Ms. 3)
- English bookplates: armorial, crests, portraits, pictorial (includes William Whewell) (Volume Bd. Ms. 4)
- English pictorial plates, G-Y (Volume Bd. Ms. 5)
- "Portrait plates" (actually mainly family crests); plates by English engravers (Volume Bd. Ms. 6)
- Bookplates of French, Irish, and Scottish notables (Volume Bd. Ms. 7)
- French, Bohemian, Belgian, German, and Italian plates (Volume Bd. Ms. 8)
- Bookplates from Argentina, Australia, Canada, Japan, Norway, Russia, and Spain (Volume Bd. Ms. 9)
- Bookplates of American statesmen, including facsimiles of the plates of Alexander Hamilton and John Quincy Adams; also, plates of the New-York [Historical?] Society (Volume Bd. Ms. 10)
- Early American bookplates, A-C, including Columbia College, circa 1700-1800 (Volume Bd. Ms. 11)
- Early American bookplates, D-J, and Harvard College bookplates, 1878-1901, circa 1700-1901 (Volume Bd. Ms. 12, pt. 1)
- Early American bookplates, McBride-Roosevelt (Volume Bd. Ms. 12, pt. 2)
- Early American bookplates, S-W (Volume Bd. Ms. 13)
- Modern American bookplates, A-B, including that of bookplate designer Elisha Brown Bird, and several other bookplates designed by him, circa 1900-1930 (Volume Bd. Ms. 14, pt. 1)
- Modern American bookplates, C-Z, including plates designed by Oscar T. Blackburn and F.C. Blank, circa 1900-1930 (Volume Bd. Ms. 14, pt. 2)
- Modern American bookplates, A-S (mainly B-C), including the plate of James Branch Cabell (Volume Bd. Ms. 15)
- Bookplates with ribbon and wreath motif; plain armorial plates, circa 1700s-1800s (Volume Bd. Ms. 16)
- Pictorial bookplates, including plates designed by John W. Evans and also Otto W. Fuhrmann, circa 1890-1950 (Volume Bd. Ms. 17)
- Modern American plates (mainly H), including plates designed by W.F. Hopson, circa 1890-1950 (Volume Bd. Ms. 18)
- Miscellaneous modern American plates (mainly pictorial), including plates designed by Dan Burne Jones, F.C. Blank, William Jordan, and J.W. Jameson, circa 1890-1950 (Volume Bd. Ms. 19)
- Modern American bookplates, mainly A and L-M, including the plate of Avery Architectural Library at Columbia University, circa 1890-1950 (Volume Bd. Ms. 20)
- Bookplates designed by Arthur N. McDonald; modern American plates, including those of the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Ohio State University Library, circa 1900-1930 (Volume Bd. Ms. 21)
- Modern bookplates, M-P, including that of publisher Thomas Bird Mosher, circa 1900-1930 (Volume Bd. Ms. 22)
- Modern bookplates, P-S, including plates designed by Howard Pyle, circa 1895-1930 (Volume Bd. Ms. 23)
- Modern American bookplates, including plates designed by Sidney L. Smith, Ismael Smith, and Leslie Victor Smith. Includes draft and proofs of a plate by Sidney L. Smith; also, several plates for Bangor (Me.) Public Library, circa 1890-1930 (Volume Bd. Ms. 24)
- Modern plates, mainly H and S-W, including plates for Harvard College Library; also, proofs of a plate designed by Daniel B. Fearing, circa 1890-1930 (Volume Bd. Ms. 25)
- Two manuscript lists describing bookplate collections; modern American plates, A-H, including plates designed by J.W. Jameson and J. Winfred Spenceley, circa 1890-1930 (Volume Bd. Ms. 26)
- Modern American plates, S-T, including plates designed by Wilbur Macey Stone, circa 1890-1930 (Volume Bd. Ms. 27)
- Modern American plates, U-W, including plates designed by Margaret Ely Webb; also, erotic bookplates, circa 1890-1940 (Volume Bd. Ms. 28)
- Bookplates designed by Edwin Davis French, A-H, including plates for the Grolier Club and Harvard University, circa 1890-1930 (Volume Bd. Ms. 29)
- Bookplates designed by Edwin Davis French, M-W, including plates for Princeton University Library and Winfred Porter Truesdell, circa 1890-1930 (Volume Bd. Ms. 30)
- Modern American bookplates, including the plate of book collector George A. Plimpton, and plates designed by Edwin Davis French, circa 1890-1930 (Volume Bd. Ms. 31)